<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<idea-plugin>
    <id>io.nimbly.mcp-companion</id>
    <name>MCP Server AI Companion</name>
    <vendor email="Maxime.HAMM@nimbly-consulting.com" url="https://github.com/maximehamm/mcp-intellij-all">Maxime HAMM</vendor>

    <description><![CDATA[

        <p>
        <b>72 tools to give your AI assistant full access to your IDE: compilation errors, test results, debug variables, run configurations, inspections, Git operations (commit, push, pull, branch, merge, rebase, cherry-pick, revert, reset, stash, blame, file history, diff between branches…), VCS changes, database schema and data, IntelliJ diff viewer, and much more.</b>
        <p>Works with any MCP-compatible AI client: <b>Claude</b> (Anthropic), <b>GitHub Copilot</b>, <b>Codex</b>, <b>Cursor</b>, <b>Windsurf</b>, and any other assistant that supports the Model Context Protocol.</p>
        </p>

        <h4>Editor &amp; Navigation</h4>
        <ul>
            <li><b>get_open_editors</b> — Open files, focused editor with caret position, and current text selection.</li>
            <li><b>get_file_problems</b> — IDE-detected errors, warnings, and infos for a file or all open editors.</li>
            <li><b>get_quick_fixes</b> — Quick fix suggestions at a specific file:line:column. Use after get_file_problems to get actionable fixes for a reported problem.</li>
            <li><b>navigate_to</b> — Opens a file and places the cursor at a given line and column.</li>
            <li><b>select_text</b> — Opens a file and selects a text range (ready to copy with Cmd+C).</li>
            <li><b>highlight_text</b> — Highlights multiple zones in a file using the IDE's search-result color (theme-aware). Press Escape to clear.</li>
            <li><b>clear_highlights</b> — Removes all highlights added by <code>highlight_text</code>.</li>
            <li><b>show_diff</b> — Opens IntelliJ's built-in diff viewer to visually compare the current content of a file with proposed new content (read-only — does not modify the file).</li>
        </ul>

        <h4>Build &amp; Tests</h4>
        <ul>
            <li><b>get_build_output</b> — Build tool window: structured error/warning tree with file names and line numbers, plus raw console text.</li>
            <li><b>get_console_output</b> — Console output from both the Run and Debug tool windows. All tabs from each window, with the active window and active tab clearly indicated.</li>
            <li><b>get_services_output</b> — All sessions from the Services tool window, grouped by node name: SQL output log, result grids with column names, and which session/tab is currently active.</li>
            <li><b>get_test_results</b> — Last test run results: passed/failed/ignored status, duration, and failure messages with stack traces.</li>
        </ul>

        <h4>Debug</h4>
        <ul>
            <li><b>debug_run_configuration</b> — Launches a run configuration in debug mode.</li>
            <li><b>get_debug_variables</b> — Local variables and their values from the current debugger stack frame (available when paused at a breakpoint).</li>
            <li><b>get_breakpoints</b> — Lists all line breakpoints with file, line number, enabled state, and condition expression.</li>
            <li><b>add_conditional_breakpoint</b> — Adds a breakpoint with an optional condition expression.</li>
            <li><b>set_breakpoint_condition</b> — Sets or removes a condition on an existing breakpoint.</li>
            <li><b>mute_breakpoints</b> — Mutes or unmutes all breakpoints in the active debug session.</li>
        </ul>

        <h4>Diagnostic &amp; Processes</h4>
        <ul>
            <li><b>get_ide_snapshot</b> — Lightweight snapshot of what the developer is currently doing: active file + caret, selection, open files, active runs/debug, indexing, background processes. Designed for frequent polling (e.g. a Claude Code hook to keep the AI aware of the current context).</li>
            <li><b>get_ide_settings</b> — Read IntelliJ IDE settings: Gradle build delegation, SDK, compiler, encoding. Pass a keyword (<code>search</code>) to filter, a <code>key</code> for direct lookup, or a <code>prefix</code> (with optional <code>depth</code>) to retrieve all settings in a subtree.</li>
            <li><b>get_intellij_diagnostic</b> — One-call diagnostic: indexing status, active notifications, running/paused processes, and <code>idea.log</code> WARN/ERROR tail. Use this first when something is not working as expected.</li>
            <li><b>get_running_processes</b> — Lists all active and paused background processes (indexing, Gradle syncs, builds, etc.).</li>
            <li><b>manage_process</b> — Pauses, resumes, or cancels a background process by title.</li>
        </ul>

        <h4>Database</h4>
        <p><em>Requires the Database Tools and SQL plugin (IntelliJ IDEA Ultimate).</em></p>
        <ul>
            <li><b>list_database_sources</b> — Lists all data sources configured in the Database tool window (name, URL, driver, user, DBMS type).</li>
            <li><b>get_database_schema</b> — Returns the schema tree already introspected by IntelliJ: namespaces → tables/views with keys, foreign keys, indexes, and optionally columns.</li>
            <li><b>execute_database_query</b> — Executes a SQL query on a configured data source and returns the results as JSON. ⚠ Disabled by default — can execute UPDATE, DELETE, DROP.</li>
        </ul>

        <h4>Gradle</h4>
        <p><em>Requires the Gradle plugin (bundled in IntelliJ IDEA Community/Ultimate and Android Studio).</em></p>
        <ul>
            <li><b>run_gradle_task</b> — Executes one or more Gradle tasks and returns a structured result (status, duration, gradleProjectPath).</li>
            <li><b>get_gradle_tasks</b> — Lists Gradle tasks discovered by IntelliJ, grouped by category (build, verification, help, …).</li>
            <li><b>refresh_gradle_project</b> — Forces a Gradle re-sync (equivalent of the 🔄 button in the Gradle tool window).</li>
            <li><b>get_gradle_dependencies</b> — Imported dependency tree per module with resolved versions and scopes.</li>
            <li><b>stop_gradle_task</b> — Cancels all currently-running Gradle tasks.</li>
            <li><b>get_gradle_project_info</b> — Wrapper version, JDK used, list of subprojects with paths and source sets — useful for monorepo reasoning.</li>
        </ul>

        <h4>Git &amp; VCS</h4>
        <ul>
            <li><b>get_vcs_changes</b> — All locally modified, added, deleted, and moved files (any VCS). Pass <code>includeDiff=true</code> to include a unified diff per file.</li>
            <li><b>get_vcs_branch</b> — Current Git branch and all local/remote branches for each repository.</li>
            <li><b>get_vcs_log</b> — Recent Git commit history: hash, author, date, subject, and changed files. Filter by file or branch.</li>
            <li><b>get_vcs_blame</b> — Line-by-line Git blame annotation: who last modified each line, when, and in which commit.</li>
            <li><b>get_vcs_file_history</b> — Commit history for a single file, with optional <code>--follow</code> to track renames across history.</li>
            <li><b>get_vcs_diff_between_branches</b> — Unified diff (or <code>--stat</code> summary) between two branches, tags, or commits.</li>
            <li><b>vcs_show_commit</b> — Full content of a Git commit: metadata, message, and unified diff of all changed files (<code>git show</code>).</li>
            <li><b>get_local_history</b> — IntelliJ Local History for a file or directory: revision list with timestamps, labels (e.g. "Before: Rename"), and optional diffs. Without a path, returns recent project-wide change events.</li>
            <li><b>vcs_stage_files</b> — Stage or unstage files in the Git index (<code>git add</code> / <code>git reset HEAD</code>).</li>
            <li><b>vcs_commit</b> — Create a Git commit from staged changes; warns if IntelliJ-tracked files are not staged; pass <code>force=true</code> to skip the check.</li>
            <li><b>vcs_push</b> — Push the current Git branch to its remote tracking branch (<code>git push</code>).</li>
            <li><b>vcs_pull</b> — Pull from the remote Git branch; pass <code>rebase=true</code> for <code>git pull --rebase</code>.</li>
            <li><b>vcs_stash</b> — Manage Git stashes: <code>action="push"</code> / <code>"pop"</code> / <code>"apply"</code> / <code>"drop"</code> / <code>"list"</code>.</li>
            <li><b>vcs_create_branch</b> — Creates a new Git branch; pass <code>checkout=true</code> (default) to switch to it immediately, and <code>from</code> to specify the base.</li>
            <li><b>vcs_checkout_branch</b> — Switches the Git working tree to an existing branch (<code>git checkout &lt;branch&gt;</code>).</li>
            <li><b>vcs_delete_branch</b> — Deletes a Git branch locally, remotely, or both. ⚠ Disabled by default — destructive.</li>
            <li><b>vcs_reset</b> — Resets the current branch to a previous commit (<code>--soft</code> / <code>--mixed</code> / <code>--hard</code>). ⚠ <code>--hard</code> overwrites the working tree.</li>
            <li><b>vcs_revert</b> — Creates a new commit that reverses the changes of a previous commit (<code>git revert</code>). Safe — does not rewrite history.</li>
            <li><b>vcs_cherry_pick</b> — Applies the changes from a specific commit on top of the current branch (<code>git cherry-pick</code>).</li>
            <li><b>vcs_fetch</b> — Fetches from one or all remotes without merging (<code>git fetch</code>); pass <code>prune=true</code> to remove deleted remote branches.</li>
            <li><b>vcs_merge_branch</b> — Merges a branch into the current one (<code>git merge</code>); pass <code>noFf=true</code> to force a merge commit.</li>
            <li><b>vcs_rebase</b> — Rebases the current branch onto another (<code>git rebase</code>); supports <code>abort=true</code> and <code>continueRebase=true</code>.</li>
            <li><b>get_vcs_conflicts</b> — Lists all conflicted files after a failed merge or rebase, with conflict type and optional file content including conflict markers.</li>
            <li><b>vcs_open_merge_tool</b> — Opens IntelliJ's built-in three-way merge tool for all conflicted files (equivalent to VCS → Git → Resolve Conflicts…).</li>
        </ul>

        <h4>General</h4>
        <ul>
            <li><b>get_mcp_companion_overview</b> — Describes all available MCP Companion tools and how to use them.</li>
            <li><b>get_project_structure</b> — Project SDK, modules, source roots, excluded folders, and module dependencies. All paths relative to project root.</li>
            <li><b>refresh_project</b> — Syncs the project build system (Gradle or Maven). Detects the build system automatically from the project root.</li>
            <li><b>execute_ide_action</b> — Executes any IntelliJ action by ID (e.g. ShowSettings, ReformatCode, GotoFile), or searches for action IDs by keyword.</li>
            <li><b>replace_text_undoable</b> — Replaces text in a file via IntelliJ's document API (supports Cmd+Z undo).</li>
            <li><b>delete_file</b> — Deletes a file from the project (undoable).</li>
        </ul>

        <h3>Example prompts</h3>
        <ul>
            <li><i>"Add a breakpoint at line 18, start the debugger, stop when i == 3, then tell me the value of jj."</i></li>
            <li><i>"Check my build output and fix the compilation errors. Make changes undoable."</i></li>
            <li><i>"Run the tests and tell me which ones failed and why."</i></li>
            <li><i>"Open Main.java and highlight all usages of variable i."</i></li>
            <li><i>"Something is wrong in IntelliJ — run a diagnostic and tell me what you see."</i></li>
            <li><i>"Stage all modified files, write a commit message based on the changes, and push to origin."</i></li>
            <li><i>"Show me the Git log for the last 10 commits and summarize what changed."</i></li>
            <li><i>"Create a feature branch from main, apply my changes, and push it."</i></li>
            <li><i>"Show me the diff between main and feature/refactor — what would be merged?"</i></li>
            <li><i>"Open the diff viewer to compare the current Util.java with this proposed refactor before I apply it."</i></li>
        </ul>

        <h3>Settings</h3>
        <p>Each tool can be individually enabled or disabled in
        <b>  Settings → Tools → MCP Server Companion</b>.</p>

        <h3>Source code</h3>
        <p>
            Source code and documentation: <a href="https://github.com/maximehamm/mcp-intellij-all">github.com/maximehamm/mcp-intellij-all</a>
        </p>

    ]]></description>

    <depends>com.intellij.modules.platform</depends>
    <depends>com.intellij.mcpServer</depends>

    <!-- Optional: Gradle tools are loaded only when the Gradle plugin is present
         (bundled in IntelliJ IDEA Community/Ultimate and Android Studio, not in
         PyCharm/WebStorm/etc.). The plugin still loads on those IDEs without Gradle. -->
    <depends optional="true" config-file="mcp-companion-gradle.xml">com.intellij.gradle</depends>

    <extensions defaultExtensionNs="com.intellij">
        <applicationService serviceImplementation="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.McpCompanionSettings"/>
        <applicationConfigurable
            parentId="tools"
            instance="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.McpCompanionConfigurable"
            id="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.configurable"
            displayName="MCP Server Companion"/>
        <postStartupActivity implementation="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.McpCompanionStartupActivity"/>
        <notificationGroup id="MCP Server Companion" displayType="BALLOON"/>
    </extensions>

    <extensions defaultExtensionNs="com.intellij.mcpServer">
        <mcpToolset implementation="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.McpCompanionToolset"/>
        <mcpToolset implementation="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.McpCompanionEditorToolset"/>
        <mcpToolset implementation="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.McpCompanionBuildToolset"/>
        <mcpToolset implementation="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.McpCompanionDebugToolset"/>
        <mcpToolset implementation="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.McpCompanionDiagnosticToolset"/>
        <mcpToolset implementation="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.McpCompanionCodeAnalysisToolset"/>
        <mcpToolset implementation="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.McpCompanionDatabaseToolset"/>
        <mcpToolset implementation="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.McpCompanionVcsToolset"/>
    </extensions>
</idea-plugin>
