<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<idea-plugin>
    <id>io.nimbly.mcp-companion</id>
    <name>MCP Server Companion</name>
    <vendor email="Maxime.HAMM@nimbly-consulting.com" url="https://github.com/maximehamm/mcp-intellij-all">Maxime HAMM</vendor>

    <description><![CDATA[
        <p>
            <b>MCP Server Companion</b> extends the built-in
            <a href="https://plugins.jetbrains.com/plugin/26071-mcp-server">JetBrains MCP Server</a>
            with additional tools for AI clients such as Claude Desktop and Cursor.
        </p>
        <p>
            MCP (Model Context Protocol) is an open standard that lets AI assistants interact directly
            with your IDE. This plugin adds tools that give your AI deeper access to your IntelliJ
            workspace — editor state, build results, run/debug output, and live variable inspection.
        </p>
        <p>
            <b>Requires:</b> the <a href="https://plugins.jetbrains.com/plugin/26071-mcp-server">JetBrains MCP Server</a>
            plugin to be installed and enabled. It is bundled in IntelliJ IDEA Ultimate 2025.1+.
            Users of Community Edition or other JetBrains IDEs can install it for free from the Marketplace.
        </p>
        <p>
            Source code and documentation: <a href="https://github.com/maximehamm/mcp-intellij-all">github.com/maximehamm/mcp-intellij-all</a>
        </p>

        <h3>Settings</h3>
        <p>Each tool can be individually enabled or disabled in <b>Settings → Tools → MCP Server Companion</b>.</p>

        <h3>Available tools</h3>

        <h4>Editor &amp; Navigation</h4>
        <ul>
            <li><b>get_open_editors</b> — Open files, focused editor with caret position, and current text selection.</li>
            <li><b>navigate_to</b> — Opens a file and places the cursor at a given line and column.</li>
            <li><b>select_text</b> — Opens a file and selects a text range (ready to copy with Cmd+C).</li>
            <li><b>highlight_text</b> — Highlights multiple zones in a file using the IDE's search-result color (theme-aware). Press Escape to clear.</li>
            <li><b>clear_highlights</b> — Removes all highlights added by <code>highlight_text</code>.</li>
        </ul>

        <h4>Build &amp; Tests</h4>
        <ul>
            <li><b>get_build_output</b> — Build tool window: structured error/warning tree with file names and line numbers, plus raw console text.</li>
            <li><b>get_run_output</b> — Console output from the Run tool window (all open tabs).</li>
            <li><b>get_test_results</b> — Last test run results: passed/failed/ignored status, duration, and failure messages with stack traces.</li>
        </ul>

        <h4>Debug</h4>
        <ul>
            <li><b>debug_run_configuration</b> — Launches a run configuration in debug mode.</li>
            <li><b>get_debug_output</b> — Console output from the Debug tool window (all open tabs).</li>
            <li><b>get_debug_variables</b> — Local variables and their values from the current debugger stack frame (available when paused at a breakpoint).</li>
            <li><b>get_breakpoints</b> — Lists all line breakpoints with file, line number, enabled state, and condition expression.</li>
            <li><b>add_conditional_breakpoint</b> — Adds a breakpoint with an optional condition expression.</li>
            <li><b>set_breakpoint_condition</b> — Sets or removes a condition on an existing breakpoint.</li>
            <li><b>mute_breakpoints</b> — Mutes or unmutes all breakpoints in the active debug session.</li>
        </ul>

        <h4>Diagnostic &amp; Processes</h4>
        <ul>
            <li><b>get_intellij_diagnostic</b> — One-call diagnostic: indexing status, active notifications, running/paused processes, and <code>idea.log</code> WARN/ERROR tail. Use this first when something is not working as expected.</li>
            <li><b>get_running_processes</b> — Lists all active and paused background processes (indexing, Gradle syncs, builds, etc.).</li>
            <li><b>manage_process</b> — Pauses, resumes, or cancels a background process by title.</li>
        </ul>

        <h4>General</h4>
        <ul>
            <li><b>get_mcp_companion_overview</b> — Describes all available MCP Companion tools and how to use them.</li>
            <li><b>get_project_structure</b> — Project SDK, modules, source roots, excluded folders, and module dependencies. All paths relative to project root.</li>
            <li><b>replace_text_undoable</b> — Replaces text in a file via IntelliJ's document API (supports Cmd+Z undo).</li>
            <li><b>delete_file</b> — Deletes a file from the project (undoable).</li>
        </ul>

        <h3>Example prompts</h3>
        <ul>
            <li><i>"Add a breakpoint at line 18, start the debugger, stop when i == 3, then tell me the value of jj."</i></li>
            <li><i>"Check my build output and fix the compilation errors. Make changes undoable."</i></li>
            <li><i>"Run the tests and tell me which ones failed and why."</i></li>
            <li><i>"Open Main.java and highlight all usages of variable i."</i></li>
            <li><i>"Something is wrong in IntelliJ — run a diagnostic and tell me what you see."</i></li>
        </ul>
    ]]></description>

    <depends>com.intellij.modules.platform</depends>
    <depends>com.intellij.mcpServer</depends>

    <extensions defaultExtensionNs="com.intellij">
        <applicationService serviceImplementation="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.McpCompanionSettings"/>
        <applicationConfigurable
            parentId="tools"
            instance="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.McpCompanionConfigurable"
            id="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.configurable"
            displayName="MCP Server Companion"/>
        <postStartupActivity implementation="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.McpCompanionStartupActivity"/>
        <notificationGroup id="MCP Server Companion" displayType="BALLOON"/>
    </extensions>

    <extensions defaultExtensionNs="com.intellij.mcpServer">
        <mcpToolset implementation="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.McpCompanionToolset"/>
    </extensions>
</idea-plugin>
