<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<idea-plugin>
    <id>io.nimbly.mcp-companion</id>
    <name>MCP Server Companion</name>
    <vendor email="Maxime.HAMM@nimbly-consulting.com" url="https://github.com/maximehamm/mcp-intellij-all">Maxime HAMM</vendor>

    <description><![CDATA[
        <p>
            <b>MCP Server Companion</b> extends the built-in
            <a href="https://plugins.jetbrains.com/plugin/26071-mcp-server">JetBrains MCP Server</a>
            with additional tools for AI clients such as Claude Desktop and Cursor.
        </p>
        <p>
            MCP (Model Context Protocol) is an open standard that lets AI assistants interact directly
            with your IDE. This plugin adds tools that give your AI deeper access to your IntelliJ
            workspace — editor state, build results, run/debug output, and live variable inspection.
        </p>
        <p>
            Source code and documentation: <a href="https://github.com/maximehamm/mcp-intellij-all">github.com/maximehamm/mcp-intellij-all</a>
        </p>

        <h3>Settings</h3>
        <p>Each tool can be individually enabled or disabled in <b>Settings → Tools → MCP Server Companion</b>.</p>
        <p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/maximehamm/mcp-intellij-all/main/docs/settings-screenshot.png" alt="MCP Server Companion Settings" width="600"/></p>

        <h3>Example questions you can ask your AI</h3>

        <b>Editor</b>
        <ul>
            <li><i>"What file am I currently editing, and what line is my cursor on?"</i></li>
            <li><i>"What is the selected code in my editor?"</i></li>
            <li><i>"What files do I have open right now?"</i></li>
            <li><i>"Look at the file I'm editing and suggest improvements for the selected code."</i></li>
        </ul>

        <b>Build</b>
        <ul>
            <li><i>"Check my build output and tell me what errors I have."</i></li>
            <li><i>"Fix the compilation errors in my project."</i></li>
            <li><i>"I have a build error — can you identify the cause and fix it? Make it undoable."</i></li>
            <li><i>"Run a build, check the result, and fix any errors."</i></li>
        </ul>

        <b>Run &amp; Debug</b>
        <ul>
            <li><i>"Run the program and show me the output."</i></li>
            <li><i>"What is the debug console showing right now?"</i></li>
            <li><i>"What are the current variable values at this breakpoint?"</i></li>
            <li><i>"Set a breakpoint at line 13, launch debug, and stop when i=3."</i></li>
        </ul>

        <b>Tests</b>
        <ul>
            <li><i>"Run the tests and tell me which ones failed and why."</i></li>
            <li><i>"Fix the failing tests."</i></li>
        </ul>

        <h3>Available tools</h3>
        <ul>
            <li><b>get_open_editors</b> — Returns all open files, the focused file with caret position, and current text selection if any.</li>
            <li>
                <b>get_build_output</b> — Returns the full content of the Build tool window:
                a structured tree of tasks/errors/warnings with file names and line numbers,
                plus the raw console text output.
            </li>
            <li>
                <b>replace_text_undoable</b> — Replaces text in a file using IntelliJ's document API,
                so the change is registered in the undo stack and can be reverted with Cmd+Z.
            </li>
            <li>
                <b>get_run_output</b> — Returns the console output from the Run tool window,
                including all open run tabs with their name and text output.
            </li>
            <li>
                <b>get_debug_output</b> — Returns the console output from the Debug tool window,
                including all open debug tabs with their name and text output.
            </li>
            <li>
                <b>get_debug_variables</b> — Returns the local variables and their values
                from the current debugger stack frame (available when paused at a breakpoint).
            </li>
            <li>
                <b>get_test_results</b> — Returns the results of the last test run:
                passed/failed/ignored status, duration, and failure messages with stack traces.
            </li>
        </ul>
    ]]></description>

    <depends>com.intellij.modules.platform</depends>
    <depends>com.intellij.mcpServer</depends>

    <extensions defaultExtensionNs="com.intellij">
        <applicationService serviceImplementation="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.McpCompanionSettings"/>
        <applicationConfigurable
            parentId="tools"
            instance="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.McpCompanionConfigurable"
            id="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.configurable"
            displayName="MCP Server Companion"/>
    </extensions>

    <extensions defaultExtensionNs="com.intellij.mcpServer">
        <mcpToolset implementation="io.nimbly.mcpcompanion.McpCompanionToolset"/>
    </extensions>
</idea-plugin>
